{"tossups": [{"question": "This organization was founded partially in response to the Springfield Race Riots of 1908, and helped investigate the Elaine Race Riot of 1919. As a result of this group\u2019s actions, racial restrictions on military officers were removed during World War One. In 1915, this group organized a protest against the pro-KKK film, <em>Birth of a Nation</em>. For ten points, name this organization founded by W. E. B. Du Bois [[doo-BOYS]] to promote civil rights for African-Americans.", "answer": "<b><u>NAACP</u></b> or the <b><u>National Association for the Advancement of Colored People</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this city, the Albizzi family came to power as a result of the Ciompi [[CHOM-pee]] Revolt in 1378. Filippo Brunelleschi [[broo-nell-ESK-ee]] won a competition to complete the Santa Maria del Fiore [[fee-OR-ay]] Cathedral in this city in 1418. This guild republic rose to European prominence as a result of its banking prowess. Patrons of this city\u2019s leader, Lorenzo, included Da Vinci and Michelangelo. For ten points, name this important Tuscan city ruled by the Medici family.", "answer": "<b><u>Florence</u></b> (or <b><u>Firenze</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The basin of the Powder River separates this mountain range from the Bighorn Mountains to the west. This mountain range provides an alternate name for the Great Sioux War of 1876. The name of the tallest peak in this mountain range was changed from Harney Peak to Black Elk Peak in 2016. Gutzon Borglum designed a monument showing the faces of four presidents in this range. For ten points, what hills contain Mount Rushmore in South Dakota?", "answer": "<b><u>Black</u></b> Hills", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In the Poetic Edda, these mythological figures gave the name Helgi to the unnamed son of King Hjorvardr [[HYOR-var-deer]]. An 11th century runestone features a carving of one of these mythological figures handing a drinking horn to the hero Sigurd. These mythological figures are said to oversee the einherjar [[AYN-hare-jar]] in the halls of Valhalla. With a name translating to \u201cchooser of the slain,\u201d for ten points, name this group of female Norse warriors.", "answer": "<b><u>Valkyrie</u></b>s", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "Arnold Constable & Company, which New York newspapers called the \u201cPalace of Trade,\u201d was the first American example of this type of business. Postmaster General John Wanamaker founded one of these businesses in Philadelphia, which housed the largest pipe organ in the world. One of these enterprises was developed from a mail-order catalog by A.C. Roebuck and Richard Sears. For ten points, name these retail companies that include Kohl\u2019s and Macy\u2019s.", "answer": "<b><u>Department store</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city's \"Maidens\" were transported to Mount Sinai Hospital in New York for treatment of keloid scars. The dome of the Industrial Promotion Hall in this city now serves as its namesake Peace Memorial. A Pulitzer Prize-winning book by John Hersey chronicles six survivors of an attack on this city, on which \u201cLittle Boy\" was dropped. For ten points, what Japanese city was devastated by an atomic bomb three days before a similar attack on Nagasaki?", "answer": "<b><u>Hiroshima</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Members of this general profession like Yuri Kondratyuk [[kon-DRAT-yuk]] and Vladimir Myasishchev [[my-ah-SISS-tchoff]] worked in locations called <em>sharashkas</em> in Soviet gulags. The so-called \"Layer Cake\" idea by a member of this profession led to the development of the RDS-37. Trofim Lysenko created fraudulent theories while working in this profession. The activist Andrei Sakharov [[SOCK-ar-off]] held, for ten points, what general profession, practitioners of which designed the Tsar Bomba?", "answer": "<b><u>Scientist</u></b> (anti-prompt on more specific answers such as \"Engineer\" or \"Physicist\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One person of this type, named Isaac Friend, planned a failed insurrection in York County, Virginia. Thomas Grantham put down a rebellion fueled in part by people with this status. Some English prisoners of war were forced into this condition, while many immigrants voluntarily entered into it. During Bacon\u2019s Rebellion, many of these people revolted against the colonial elite. For ten points, name these workers who entered into voluntary servitude.", "answer": "<b><u>Indentured servant</u></b>s (accept [indentured servitude[/a], do not accept or prompt on \"slavery\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This instrument was played by the Black musician George Bridgetower, the dedicatee of Beethoven\u2019s <em>Kreutzer Sonata</em>. Erich Wolfgang Korngold\u2019s concerto for this instrument was first played by Jascha [[YOSH-ah]] Heifetz. A 19th-century Italian who wrote 24 caprices for this instrument was believed by some to have sold his soul to the Devil. Niccolo Paganini played one of these instruments crafted by Stradivarius. For ten points, name this highest-pitched string instrument.", "answer": "<b><u>Violin</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In a 1958 book, this man faces a \"good son\" and \"good monk\" crisis in which he is twice born and his soul transformed. In that book, this man suffers an \"identity crisis\" in which, during a choir practice at a monastery, he shouts \"I am not!\" Following a similar work about Mahatma Gandhi, psychologist Erik Erikson wrote a psychobiography of this man, who challenged the Catholic Church at the Diet [[DEE-et]] of Worms [[VURMS]]. For ten points, name this Reformation leader who wrote the 95 Theses in Wittenberg, Germany.", "answer": "Martin <b><u>Luther</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Bicentennial of this colony was celebrated in the Grand National Jubilee. Nikole Hannah-Jones places the consequences of slavery at the center of US history, beginning with this colony, in <em>The 1619 Project</em>. Tobacco seeds were brought to this colony by John Rolfe in the Third Supply, and this colony earlier had faced the \"Starving Time.\" Located a few miles southwest of Williamsburg, for ten points, name this first permanent English settlement in America.", "answer": "<b><u>Jamestown</u></b>, Virginia", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Major Hubert-Joseph Henry made a dramatic testimony during this event in which the Panizzardi telegram was investigated. Armand du Paty de Clam was promoted in this event, which was resolved when Henri Brisson resigned. \u00c9mile Zola wrote <em>J'Accuse</em> during this event, increasing public pressure to reopen it. The real traitor in this event was Ferdinand Esterhazy. For ten points, name this French scandal in which a Jewish officer was wrongly convicted.", "answer": "<b><u>Dreyfus Affair</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "One self-critique of this work by its composer called it \u201cvery loud and noisy and completely without artistic merit.\u201d This piece was conducted by that composer at the opening of Carnegie Hall in 1891. This work debuted at the Cathedral of Christ the Saviour, which was later demolished on the orders of Josef Stalin. For ten points, name this Pyotr Tchaikovsky concert piece that features chimes and cannons and is often played as an accompaniment to fireworks displays.", "answer": "The Year <b><u>1812</u></b> Solemn <b><u>Overture</u></b>, Op. 49", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This country was once led by \"The Madman Who Loves,\u201d Abdal\u00e1 Bucaram. With a neighbor, this country's president of Lebanese descent, Jamil Mahuad, signed the Brasilia Presidential Act. After a 1972 coup, this country implemented a \"Return to the Constitution Plan.\u201d One party in this country was named \"Alfaro Lives, Dammit!\u201d In 2017, this country's president, Len\u00edn Moreno, succeeded Rafael Correa. For ten points, name this South American nation, the first to call for independence in 1809.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Ecuador</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Using a magical hook made of ancestor bones, a trickster figure of these people raised an archipelago. One of this culture\u2019s legends takes place at the lagoon, Mata o le Alelo, and tells the story of Sina, who fell in love with an eel who once held the title, Tui Viti. Paul Gauguin painted an interpretation of this culture\u2019s ghosts staring at a nude girl in his <em>Spirit</em> <em>of the Dead Watching</em>. For ten points, name this people group of the Pacific whose divine figures include Maui and Pele.", "answer": "<b><u>Polynesia</u></b>n (accept more specific people like <b><u>Hawaii</u></b>ans, <b><u>Tahiti</u></b>ans, or <b><u>Samoa</u></b>ns)  Kohara is the Polynesian goddess and original ancestor of this fish from the mackerel family, important to the seafaring people, some species of which are endangered due to overfishing.  ANSWER: <b><u>Tuna</u></b> (accept <b><u>Tunny</u></b>)   With Guntram, a leader of these people signed the Pact of Andelot. One noble of (6)  these people tried to kill Rigunth by slamming a chest shut, and that woman, Fredegund, also ordered Sigebert I's assassination. A queen of these people, Brunhilda, was executed by being pulled apart by horses. Gregory of Tours documented these people's Merovingian Dynasty. Pepin the Short and Clovis were rulers of, for ten points, what Germanic people who gave their name to France?  ANSWER: <b><u>Franks</u></b> (accept <b><u>Merovingian</u></b>s Dynasty before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Zero-tolerance on this border was implemented in Operation Streamline. This border was changed in the Chamizal Dispute due to river shifts. The Big Bend National Park lies on this border, and the International Boundary and Water Commission deals with water rights on this border. This border was first fixed in the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, and, more recently, Donald Trump proposed enhancing a wall on this border. For ten points, name this border that includes a portion of the Rio Grande.", "answer": "<b><u>United States-Mexico</u></b> border (accept <b><u>US</u></b> or <b><u>USA</u></b> for <b><u>United States</u></b>; accept <b><u>United Mexican States</u></b> or <b><u>EUM</u></b> for <b><u>Mexico</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "A biography by Richard Norton Smith takes its title from this former president\u2019s \u201cUncommon Man\u201d speech, delivered at Wilmington College in 1948. This man was appointed by Calvin Coolidge to oversee relief efforts after the Great Mississippi Flood of 1927. During a severe economic downturn, shantytowns named for this president popped up across the nation. For ten points, name this 31st US president who served a single term during the Great Depression.", "answer": "Herbert <b><u>Hoover</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Shot and killed Alexander Hamilton in an 1804 duel.", "answer": "Aaron <b><u>Burr</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Was not involved in the Watergate scandal but resigned in 1973.", "answer": "Spiro <b><u>Agnew</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Feuded with Andrew Jackson about tariffs before resigning.", "answer": "John C. <b><u>Calhoun</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Gave the \u201cCheckers\u201d speech following a campaign fund controversy.", "answer": "Richard <b><u>Nixon</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Was implicated in the Whiskey Ring under Ulysses Grant.", "answer": "Schuyler <b><u>Colfax</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Infamously misspelled the word \u201cpotato\u201d", "answer": "Dan <b><u>Quayle</u> </b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Arrived too late to make the tie-breaking vote for Coolidge's nominee for Attorney General.", "answer": "Charles G. <b><u>Dawes</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Was replaced on the incumbent ticket by Harry Truman due to his incompetence.", "answer": "<b><u>H</u></b>enry <b><u>Wallace</u></b> (prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "English capital where the Tallow Chandlers Company was located.", "answer": "<b><u>London</u></b>, England, United Kingdom", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Man who is celebrated on Candlemas as well as December 25th, his birthday.", "answer": "<b><u>Jesus</u></b> Christ", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Natural material used for candles that comes from honey making insects.", "answer": "<b><u>Beeswax</u></b> (prompt on \"wax\")", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Aquatic mammal hunted to near extinction for the candle-making material harvested from its head cavity.", "answer": "Sperm <b><u>whale</u> </b>  Type of wax made from the material that James Young distilled from coal and oil (5)  shales.  ANSWER: <b><u>Paraffin</u></b> Wax", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "1840 London event involving a woman wearing a William Dyce-designed dress, during which loyal households burned candles.", "answer": "<b><u>Wedding</u></b> of Queen <b><u>Victoria</u></b> and Prince Albert (accept <b><u>Marriage</u></b> in place of \"Wedding\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Upstate New York city named for a Sicilian city known for candle manufacturing.", "answer": "<b><u>Syracuse</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Largest candle-maker in the UK who pioneered steam distillation in manufacturing.", "answer": "<b><u>Price</u></b>'s Patent Candles", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Engineering"}, {"question": "Egyptian river where the Sea People were repelled after the Battle of the Delta.", "answer": "<b><u>Nile</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "First name of the pharaoh who expelled the Sea People and shares his name with an earlier \u201cGreat\u201d pharaoh.", "answer": "<b><u>Ramesses</u></b> III", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "First capital of the New Kingdom which shares its name with a Greek city-state.", "answer": "<b><u>Thebes</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Queen depicted on a famous bust displayed in Berlin since 1912.", "answer": "<b><u>Nefertiti</u> </b>  Semitic people expelled by the New Kingdom and associated with the Israelites by (5)  Josephus.  ANSWER: <b><u>Hyksos</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Pharaoh who introduced the monotheistic cult of Atenism.", "answer": "<b><u>Akhenaten</u></b> (accept <b><u>Amenhotep IV</u></b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Temple complex built by Amenhotep III and dedicated to the mother goddess Mut.", "answer": "<b><u>Luxor</u></b> Temple", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "Region known as \u201cThe Land of the Gods,\u201d to which Hatshepsut sponsored many voyages in search of gold and ivory.", "answer": "Land of <b><u>Punt</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this year, Jim Sasser and Harris Wofford lost their seats in the Senate. A</u></b> <b><u>document released in this year proposed the Citizen Legislature Act, which would</u></b> <b><u>have introduced congressional term limits. In this year, Alabama senator Richard (+)</u></b> <b>Shelby switched parties and became a Republican. The Heritage Foundation worked with Larry Hunter, Tom DeLay, and Newt Gingrich in this year to write the (*) </b>Contract with America. For ten points, name this midterm election year during Bill Clinton's first term.", "answer": "<b><u>1994</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man lost at the Battle of Grand Turk in the Turks and Caicos. C. K. Shorter</u></b> <b><u>claims that the Bronte family of literary fame changed their surname to associate</u></b> <b><u>themselves with this man, the Duke of Bront\u00e9. With Lord Jervis, this man attacked (*)</u></b> <b>C\u00e1diz and led an amphibious attack on Santa Cruz de Tenerife. On the </b><em><b>Victory</b></em><b>, this man engaged the </b><em><b>Bucentaure</b></em><b> and signaled, \"England expects (*) </b>that every man will do his duty.\u201d For ten points, name this British admiral who was killed at Trafalgar.", "answer": "Horatio <b><u>Nelson</u></b> (accept 1st Viscount <b><u>Nelson</u></b>, accept 1st Duke of <b><u>Bront\u00e9</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1034, this river flooded following heavy rainfall at Henglong. This river</u></b> <b><u>carries sediment from the Loess plateau and has a large bend in the Ordos Loop.</u></b> <b><u>Historically, this river once went through Dalu Lake and Daye Lake but shifted due to</u></b> <b><u>floods, one of which ended the (+)</u> Xin [[SHIN]] Dynasty of Wang Mang. 890,000 people died when this river flooded after the KMT destroyed levees to stop the (*) </b>Japanese invasion. For ten points, name this second-longest Chinese river known for its muddy color.", "answer": "<b><u>Yellow</u></b> River (accept <b><u>Huang He</u></b> [[HWONG-HUH]])", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>A leader of this country claimed that its own citizens would \u201ceat grass,\u201d if</u></b> <b><u>necessary, to develop its own nuclear arsenal if a rival nation did so. Baitullah</u></b> <b><u>Mehsud was accused of ordering the 2007 assassination of this country\u2019s former</u></b> <b><u>prime minister, (+)</u> Benazir Bhutto. In 1940, Muhammad Ali Jinnah worked to pass the Lahore Resolution, demanding that the UK grant independence to this nation, separate from its (*) </b>majority-Hindu neighbor. For ten points, name this primarily Muslim country created by the Partition of India.", "answer": "Islamic Republic of <b><u>Pakistan</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Aaron Schock, a congressman from this state, resigned after being accused of</u></b> <b><u>buying luxury items with government money. Mike Madigan, Speaker of the House in</u></b> <b><u>this state, faced a 2020 investigation over a bribery scandal and was urged to step</u></b> <b><u>down by Governor J. B. (+)</u> Pritzker. An FBI operation called Silver Shovel discovered that aldermen in this state\u2019s (*) </b>Cook County were complicit in illegal activities. For ten points, name this state where George Ryan and Rod Blagojevich [[blah-GOY-eh-vitch]] once governed from Springfield.", "answer": "<b><u>Illinois</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>Pope Clement II may have been murdered using tainted sugar that caused this</u></b> <b><u>condition. Caravaggio's violent behavior might indicate he also died of this condition.</u></b> <b><u>The</u> </b><em><b><u>Washington Post</u></b></em><b><u> claimed correlation between this condition and the decrease in</u></b> <b><u>crime, due to a (+)</u> substance being removed from paint and gasoline. A hypothesis concerning the collapse of the Roman Empire blames this condition occurring due to (*) </b>pipes. For ten points, name this type of metal poisoning.", "answer": "<b><u>Lead</u></b> poisoning", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {"question": "<b><u>A temple for this deity built during the reign of Augustus was one of the first</u></b> <b><u>discoveries in Pompeii. Helena Blavatsky wrote about this deity</u> </b><em><b><u>Unveiled</u></b></em><b><u> as part of</u></b> <b><u>the Theosophists. The use of model boats in medieval Carnival festivals was argued to</u></b> <b><u>have been derived from the cult of this deity. This (*)</u> goddess was invoked in the </b><em><b>Ephesian Tale</b></em><b> to protect virginity and revived her husband after he was torn into 14 pieces by (*) </b>Set. For ten points, name this Egyptian goddess, the wife of Osiris.", "answer": "<b><u>Isis</u></b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man sent \"sincere congratulations\" that an attack of \"armed hordes\" had</u></b> <b><u>been stopped \"without appealing to friendly powers for help.\u201d In 1895, this man was</u></b> <b><u>compelled to send a cruiser to Delagoa Bay, and a telegram from him to Johannes (*)</u></b> <b>Kruger was possibly written by Adolf Marschall von Bieberstein. In the </b><em><b>Daily </b><b>Telegraph</b></em><b> Affair, this man called the English \"mad as March hares.\u201d Before World War One, this man sent (*) </b>Nicholas II the Willy-Nicky letters. For ten points, name this German Kaiser.", "answer": "<b><u>Wilhelm II</u></b> (accept <b><u>William II</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>These people formed the National Strike Council and held the Silence March.</u></b> <b><u>In a speech against these people, a president claimed, \"No one has rights against</u></b> <b><u>Mexico.\u201d Gustavo D\u00edaz Ordaz faced these people in their 1968 (+)</u> Mexican Movement. These people were targeted in Operation Galeana by the Olimpio Battalion in a massacre investigated by Elena Poniatowskia. Many of these people were killed in the Tlatelolco Massacre. These people launched the \u201cYo Soy 132\u201d movement at (*) </b>UNAM. For ten points, name these people who went to colleges and universities.", "answer": "<b><u>Student</u></b>s in Mexico", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}], "bonuses": []}